A Guide to the Nelson C. Davis Papers FA048
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson C. Davis papers
1895-1935
Rockefeller Archive Center
Davis, Nelson C.
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board
Rockefeller Foundation
FA048
23.1 Cubic Feet 33 document cases
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The material in this collection has been arranged in three series:
Series 1 - Personal Papers (1913-1933)
Series 2 - Professional Papers (1921-1933)
Series 3 - Printed Matter
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Caryl Davis was born in Osceola, Nebraska, on August 26, 1892, the posthumous son of John E. Davis. His mother remarried and moved to Ceres, California, in 1896, where young Davis attended local public schools. After graduating from high school, he entered the Hospital Corps of the United States Army and spent two years (1910-1912) in the Philippine Islands. While in the armed forces, his interest turned toward the study of tropical diseases, which was to constitute his life's work. Between 1914 and 1917 he completed undergraduate work at The University of California at Berkeley, and immediately entered medical studies at The University of California Medical School.
On January 12, 1917, he married Mary Faye Caulkins of Ceres, California, then also a student at The University of California at Berkeley. This marriage was to produce five sons, one of whom died in infancy (1923) during Dr. Davis's first period of service in Brazil.
After a short period of inactive military service during World War I, Dr. Davis received a Hooper Foundation fellowship in medical research (1918) and did studies of liver pathology with Dr. George H. Whipple. This research resulted in his first published articles. He also briefly served as an assistant in the Department of Pathology at The University of California before receiving his M.D. in 1921.
In May 1922, Dr. Davis became a regular member of the staff of the International Health Board of The Rockefeller Foundation. His appointment as Junior Field Director carried him to Porto Alegre, Brazil where he participated in hookworm control and related programs. He was reassigned to malaria work in Argentina, where he was stationed intermittently from July 1925 to July 1927. This assignment increased his interest in medical entomology, and he continued to produce articles on anopheline mosquitoes and malaria for the rest of his life.
Upon returning to the United States on leave in the summer of 1927, he attended courses at The School of Hygiene and Public Health of The Johns Hopkins University. After a brief supplementary period of study (March-May 1931), he was awarded the degree of Doctor of Public Health from that institution.
At the end of his first study leave (July 1928), Dr. Davis undertook the establishment of a laboratory at Bahia, Brazil, to carry on yellow fever research in South America and also to conduct laboratory studies for the yellow fever control service maintained jointly by the Government of Brazil and The Rockefeller Foundation. Through his research it was established that yellow fever was transmitted by several species of mosquitoes other than Aedes aegypti, the previously recognized agent of infection. His collaborators in this work included Drs. Martin Frobisher, Jr., Raymond C. Shannon, J. Austin Kerr, and Henry W. Kumm. Dr. Paul A. Lewis, one of his early coworkers at the Bahia laboratory, died of yellow fever early in 1929 - one of the noted martyrs to that disease. Dr. Davis contracted it at the same time, but survived.
Complications arising from this bout with yellow fever led to Dr. Davis's own death four years later. During his second period of study at Johns Hopkins (1931), his gall bladder had been removed. Although in steady pain, he continued his heavy load of research and leadership of the Bahia laboratory until his sudden death on October 20, 1933, from acute edema.
Scope and Contents note
The Nelson C. Davis Collection will be of interest both to the historian of medical research and of medical education. The lecture notes and class papers prepared by Dr. Davis at all levels of his training have been preserved in this collection. Also included are drafts of papers, some of them unpublished, at various stages of preparation, reprints of his published articles, and a wide variety of supporting research materials (such as reprints and periodicals), many taken from Portuguese- or Spanish-language publications. A substantial portion of his laboratory diary (kept at Bahia from 1928 to 1933) can be found in this collection as well as a number of field notebooks and records of experiments. Personal correspondence, however, has been rather scantily preserved.
Significant correspondents in this collection include Mark F. Boyd, Rollin C. Dean, John H. Janney, Robert H. Kirk, Henry W. Kumm, E. R. Rickard, Francis M. Root, F. F. Russell, Wilbur A. Sawyer, Fred L. Soper, and George K. Strode.
Related Archival Materials note
A complete transcript of the laboratory duties and of much of the field notes kept by Dr. Davis at the Bahia laboratory can be found in the archives of The Rockefeller Foundation (Record Group 1.1, Series 305.O). Correspondence with Rockefeller Foundation officials -- especially F. F. Russell and Fred L. Soper -- may also be found in the Foundation archives (Record Group 1.1, Series 305.O and 305.I). Also available are a large number of photographs relating to the work of the Bahia laboratory contemporaneous with Dr. Davis's period of service there -- many of which originally accompanied his reports to the Foundation.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 28
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Nelson C. Davis were deposited with The Rockefeller Foundation Archives by his son, Franklin Davis, on December 6, 1971.
Medical research -- Salvador (Brazil); Yellow fever; Diseases; Medical research; Medical education; Medical research -- Brazil; Malaria; Hookworm disease
- Personal Papers, 1913-1933; 1
  Arrangement note
  Series 1 is divided into 5 subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Correspondence Subseries 2 - Financial Material Subseries 3 - Class Notes and Papers Subseries 4 - Articles Subseries 5 - Plates and Drawings
  Scope and Contents note
  The material contained in this series consists of documents generated by Dr. Davis as a private person or in the course of his training and research. Included in this series are correspondence, financial material, class notes and papers, and scientific articles in various stages of development (from manuscript to reprint). Papers of his wife, Mrs. Mary Faye Davis, or his sons Donald and Irvine, have also been included in Subseries 1 and 3.
  - Personal Papers - Correspondence, 1917-1933; 1.1
    Material in this subseries has been filed chronologically; incoming and outgoing correspondence have not been filed together.
    This subseries consists of handwritten or typed letters to Dr. Davis with carbon copies of his replies. The bulk of this correspondence is not of a personal nature, but is rather in the nature of scientific inquiries or reports on activities. A few letters to and from Dr. Davis's sons, Donald and Irvine Davis, have been included as part of the regular correspondence; other of their papers not in the nature of correspondence have been included separately at the end of this subseries.
    - Correspondence, November 14, 1917-March 12, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, March 15, 1924-May 15, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, May 16, 1928-August 27, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, August 29, 1929-September 20, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, October 30, 1930-May 8, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, May 8, 1931-October 26, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Children's Papers, circa 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Drawings and class papers by Donald and Irvine Davis.
  - Personal Papers - Financial Material, 1922-1931; 1.2
    The material in this subseries has been arranged chronologically.
    This subseries consists mainly of income tax returns, insurance vouchers, receipts, bank statements, and records of purchase.
    - Financial Material, April 22, 1922-December 16, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Financial Material, January 25, 1930-August 27, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal Papers - Class Notes and Papers, 1913-1931; 1.3
    The material in this subseries has been arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by course title; since much of it can be dated by internal evidence only, this order must be regarded as approximate for the whole.
    This subseries consists of lecture and laboratory notebooks, class papers, course syllabi, and other classroom material used by Dr. Davis.
    Dr. Davis's undergraduate training took place at The University of California at Berkeley (1914-1917); he received his M.D. from The University of California Medical School in 1921. His further education at The Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health (1927-1928, 1931) earned him the degree of Doctor of Public Health.
    Class notes and papers by Mrs. Mary Faye Davis have been filed at the end of this subseries.
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Zoology 1A - Class Paper, 1914 Chemistry 1 A and B - Lecture and Lab Notes, c. 1913-1914 Chemistry 8 A and B - Lecture Notes, c. 1914-1915
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Chemistry 9 - Syllabus, 1915-1916
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Biology - Lab Notes and Papers, 1916 Cytology - Class Paper, 1916
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Biochemistry 101M - Lecture Notes, 1917
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Biochemistry 101M - Lab Notes, 1917 Physiology 104M - Lecture Notes, 1917
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Physiology 104M - Lab Notes, 1917
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Zoology - Lecture Notes and Class Papers, c. 1916-1917
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Zoology - Class Papers, c. 1916-1917 Bacteriology - Lecture Notes, n.d.
    - Class Notes - Undergraduate (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Botany - Lecture Notes, n.d. Unknown course - Class Papers, n.d.
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 3, Folder 19)
      General Medicine, 1920 Immunology, 1920 Dermatology, c. 1920 Parasitology, c. 1920
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Clinical Pathology Conferences, 1919-1921
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Pediatrics, c. 1919-1920 Neuropsychiatry, c. 1920
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Reading Notes, c. 1920 Examination of Patients, 1920-1921 Orthopedic Surgery, c. 1920 X-ray, c. 1920-1921
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Urology, c. 1920-1921 Laryngology, c. 1920-1921 Opthamology, c. 1920-1921
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 4, Folder 24)
      Neurosurgery and General Surgery, 1920 Military Surgery, 1921 Clinical Pathology, c. 1921 Surgical Pathology, c. 1921 (this notebook apparently combines notes from several courses)
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Zoology, 1921 Entomology, 1921
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 4, Folder 26)
      Experimental Notes, 1921-1922 Personal Hygiene, n.d.
    - Class Notes - Medical School (Box 4, Folder 27)
      Unknown Course - Notebook, n.d. Unknown Course - Papers and Notes, n.d.
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Chemical Hygiene, 1927 Nutrition, 1927
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Bacteriology, 1927
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 30)
      Public Health Administration, 1927
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 31)
      Epidemiology, 1928
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 32)
      Epidemiology, 1928 Statistics, 1928
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 33)
      Protozoology, 1928
      Related Materials
      See also Box 5, Folder 31.
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 34)
      Sanitary Engineering - Problems in Sanitation, 1928
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 35)
      Sanitary Engineering - Refuse Disposal, 1928 Sanitary Engineering - Sewage Disposal, 1928 Sanitary Engineering - Water Supplies, 1928
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 5, Folder 36)
      Sanitary Engineering - Water Supplies, 1928 Filterable Viruses - Syllabus, 1929
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Blank Forms - Baltimore City Health Department Bureau of Bacteriology
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 38)
      Blank Forms - Bureau of Chemistry and Food
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Blank Forms - Bureau of Communicable Diseases
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 40)
      Blank Forms - Bureau of Nursing Bureau of Sanitation
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 41)
      Blank Forms - Bureau of Vital Statistics Executive Office and Epidemiologist
    - Class Notes - Johns Hopkins (Box 6, Folder 42)
      Unknown Class - Lecture Notes, c. 1927-1928 Epidemiology - Summaries for Class Discussion, 1931 Unknown Class - Stray Sheets, 1928?
    - Class Notes - Correspondence Courses (Box 6, Folder 43)
      Spanish, 1926
    - Class Notes - Correspondence Courses (Box 6, Folder 44)
      German, 1931-1932
    - Class Notes - Mrs. Mary Faye Davis (Box 7, Folder 45)
      Class Papers and Lecture Notebooks, 1913-1917
    - 64 Pages of Graphs and Notes for a Course in Epidemiology at The Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health, 1928 (Box 33, Folder 306)
  - Personal Papers - Articles, 1921-1933; 1.4
    Materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically based on date of publication, followed by completed articles left unpublished.
    This subseries consists of manuscript and typescript drafts or copies of studies by Dr. Davis on various entomological or medical topics. Dr. Davis's dissertation for The Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health ("Studies upon 'Aedes aegypti' at Various Temperatures," May 1931) is included here, as it remained unpublished as a whole, although two articles were later derived from it. This subseries closes with copies of Dr. Davis's articles in reprint form.
    The following articles are not represented in this collection:
    1919 Davis, N.C. and Whipple, G.H. - The influence of fasting and various diets on the liver injury effected by chloroform anesthesia. Archives of Internal Medicine, 23:612-635, 1919.
    Davis, N.C. and Whipple, G.H. - The influence of drugs and chemical agents on the liver necrosis of chloroform anaesthesia. Paper II. Archives of Internal Medicine, 23:636-654, 1919.
    Davis, N.C., Hall, C.C. and Whipple, G.H. - The rapid construction of liver cell protein in a strict carbohydrate diet contrasted with fasting; mechanism of protein sparing action of carbohydrate. Archives of Internal Medicine, 23:689-710, 1919.
    Davis, N.C. and Whipple, G.H. - Liver regeneration following chloroform injury as influenced by various diets; mechanism of protein sparing action of fat. Archives of Internal Medicine, 23:711-722, 1919.
    1930 Shannon, R.C. and Davis, N.C. - Observations on the anophelini (culicidae) of Bahia, Brazil. Annals of the Entomological Society of America, 23:467-505, No. 3, September.
    1933 Notes on some South American mosquitoes. II. The genus 'Mansonia', subgenus 'Rhynchotaonia'. Annals of the Entomological Society of America, Columbus. 26:619-639. December 1933.
    Transmission of yellow fever virus by 'Colux Fatigens' Weidemann. Annals of the Entomological Soc. of America, Columbus. 26:491-495. September 1933.
    The survival of yellow fever virus in ticks. American Journal of Tropical Medicine, Baltimore. 13:547-554. November 1933.
    - Articles - Manuscript or Typescript, May 1924-March 1926 (Box 7, Folder 46)
      Davis, N.C. Experience with the Stoll egg counting method in an area lightly infested with hookworm. The American Journal of Hygiene, 4:226-236, No. 3, May 1924.
      Davis, N.C. The influence of diet upon the liver injury produced by carbon tetrachloride. Journal of Medical Research, 44:601-614, No. 5, September 1924.
      Davis, N.C. Hookworm infection as influenced by the wearing of shoes. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 5:81-86, No. 1, January 1925. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. A Field Study of Mountain Malaria in Brazil. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:119-138, No. 1, January 1926.
      Davis, N.C. Notes on the female hypopygia of anopheline mosquitoes, with special reference to some Brazilian species. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:1-22, March 1926 Supplement.
      Davis, N.C. Study on the dispersion of resting anopheline mosquitoes from dwellings in Brazil. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:23-35, March 1926 Supplement. 2 copies.
    - Articles - Manuscript or Typescript, May 1926-March 1929 (Box 7, Folder 47)
      Davis, N.C. and Boyd, M.F. The occurrence of Quartan malaria in the low coastal regions of the state of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. An epidemiological study. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 6:195-203, No. 3, May 1926.
      Davis, N.C. and Shannon, R.C. The habits of 'Anopheles rondoni' in the Argentine Republic. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:448-456, No. 3, May 1928.
      Davis, N.C. A consideration of variability in the Nyssorhynchus group of the genus Anopheles. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:539-563, No. 4, July 1928.
    - Articles - Manuscript or Typescript, March 1929-November 1931 (Box 7, Folder 48)
      Davis, N.C. and Rickard, E.R. Plan de lucha contra la malaria urbana en el norte argentina. (A Plan of Attack Applicable to Urban Malaria in Northern Argentina). Semana medica, 1:652-658, March 14, 1929.
      Davis, N.C. Use experimental de uma vaccina cloroformada contra a febre amarella. (Experimental Use of a Chloroform-Treated Yellow Fever Vaccine). Brasil-Medico, 45:268, No. 12, March 21, 1931.
      Davis, N.C. and Shannon, R.C. Further attempts to transmitt yellow fever with mosquitoes of South America. The American Journal of Hygiene, 14:715-722, No. 3, November 1931.
      Davis, N.C. and Kumm, H.H.W. Further incrimination of 'Anophelos darlingi' Root as a transmitter of malaria. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 12:93-95, No. 1, January 1932. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. The effects of heat and of cold upon 'Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti'. The American Journal of Hygiene, 16:177-191, No. 1, July 1932. 2 copies.
    - Articles - Manuscript or Typescript, Apparently Unpublished, circa 1923 - circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Articles - Thesis - "Studies upon 'Aedes aegypti' at Various Temperatures" - Partial Typescript, May 1931 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Articles - Reprints, June 1921-March 1926 (Box 8, Folder 51)
      Davis, N.C. The effect of cyanids and of organic oxidizing agents on the liver injury caused by chloroform. Archives of Internal Medicine, 28:20-36, 1921. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. and Whipple, G.H. Liver regeneration following chloroform injury as influenced by the feeding of casein of gelatin. Archives of Internal Medicine, 28:679-687, 1921.
      Davis, N.C. and Hall, I.C. Influence of calcium chloride upon experimental botulism. Journal of Experimental Medicine, 37:585-599, April 1923.
      Davis, N.C. and Reich, W.W. Coccidial oocysts from domestic animals in California. Journal of Parasitology, 10:137-146, March 1924.
      Davis, N.C. The influence of diet upon the liver injury produced by carbon tetrachloride. Journal of Medical Research, 44:601-614, No. 5, September 1924. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. hookworm infection as influenced by the wearing of shoes. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 5:81-86, No. 1, January 1925.
      Davis, N.C. A Field Study of Mountain Malaria in Brazil. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:119-138, No. 1, January 1926. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. Notes on the female hypopygia of anopheline mosquitoes with special reference to some Brazilian species. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:1-22, March 1926 Supplement.
      Davis, N.C. Study on the dispersion of resting anopheline mosquitoes from dwellings in Brazil. The American Journal of Hygiene, 6:23-35, March 1926 Supplement.
    - Articles - Reprints, May 1926-May 1928 (Box 8, Folder 52)
      Davis, N.C. and Boyd, M.F. The occurrence of Quartan malaria in the low coastal regions of the state of Rio de Janiero, Brazil. An epidemiological study. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 6:195-203, No. 3, May 1926. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C., Cabarrou, F.G. and Laino, F. Estudios entomologicos en su relacion con la lucha antipaludica. Boletin del Instituto de Clinica quirurgica, Buenos Aires, 3:733-743, 1927. 2 copies.
      Shannon, R.C., Davis, N.C. and del Ponte, E. La distribucion del "Anopheles pseudopunctipennis" y su relacion con el paludismo en la Argentina. Anales del Departemento nacional de higiene, Buenos Aires, 33:56-88, 1927. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C., Lobe, M.M. and Cabarrou, F.G. Lucha antipaludica en Medinas (Prov. de Tucuman, Republica Argentina). Semana medica, 1:467-485, February 24, 1927.
      Shannon, R.C. and Davis, N.C. Condiciones de reproduccion de Anopheles pseudopunctipennis en la provincia de Tucuman durante la estacion seca. Revista del Instituto Bacteriologico, 4:662-678, No. 7, March 1927. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. 'Anopheles pseudopuncitipennis' as a malaria transmitter in Northern Argentine Republic. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 7:167-176, No. 3, May 1927. 2 copies.
      Davis N.C. and Shannon, R.C. The habits of 'Anopheles rondioni' in the Argentine Republic. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:448-456, No. 3, May 1928. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. A study on the transmission of filaria in northern Argentina. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:457-466, No. 3, May 1928.
    - Articles - Reprints, May 1928-March 1930 (Box 8, Folder 53)
      Davis, N.C. Notes on the development of ovarian follicles in Argentine anopheles. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:467-475, No. 3, May 1928. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. A consideration of variability in the Nyssorhynchus group of the genus Anopheles. The American Journal of Hygiene, 8:539-563, No. 4, July 1928. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. and Shannon, R.C. The blood feeding habits of 'Anopheles pseudopunctipennis' in Northern Argentina. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 8:443-447, No. 5, September 1928. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. and Rickard, E.R. Plan de lucha contra la malaria urbana en el norte argentina. (A Plan of Attack Applicable to Urban Malaria in Northern Argentina). Semana medica, 1:652-658, March 14, 1929. 2 copies.
      Davis, N.C. and Burke, A.W. Studies on South American yellow fever. I. The strains of virus in use at the Yellow Fever Laboratory in Bahia, Brazil. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 49:975-984, No. 6, June 1, 1929.
      Davis, N.C. Studies on South American yellow fever. II. Immunity of recovered monkeys to African virus. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 49:985-991, No. 6, June 1, 1929.
      Davis, N.C. and Shannon, R.C. Studies on South American yellow fever. III. Transmission of the virus to Brazilian monkeys. Preliminary observations. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 50:81-85, No. 1, July 1, 1929.